Dr. Thomas Arend

46 Ashbury Street • San Francisco, CA 94117 • (415) 689-0928 • mail@thomasarend.com

Summary

Seasoned Technology Product Executive and Entrepreneur with over 25 years of experience in the tech industry as Chief Product Officer, International Product Leader, Corporate Strategist, People Manager, Mentor and Coach, Founder, Innovator, Start-up Advisor, Software Engineer, and Platform Architect. Hands-on in all product development and engineering processes, Scrum Master, User Experience and Design expert. Passionate Leader, Product Manager and User Advocate, Entrepreneurial Thinker, and Team Lead with a track record of delivering exceptional results by interacting closely with users, Engineering, User Research, Design, Data. Focus on creating delightful web-based experiences and mobile consumer and enterprise apps. Ph.D. in Artificial Intelligence / Machine Learning; M.S. in Computer Science and Mathematics.

Professional Experience

5/2020 - present

Johnson & Johnson, San Francisco, California **Senior Director of Product**

- Leading the global Digital Health Technology product team at J&J whose goal is to build, launch, and scale transformative digital healthcare solutions globally across J&J's pharma, consumer health, and medical device businesses
- Together with my team, I reimagine how health and well-care are accessed, delivered, managed, and experienced at scale
- I turn advances in technology into products that have the potential to create a dramatic positive impact for many people in the world and to help us live longer, healthier, happier lives

1/2018 - 5/2020

Facebook, Inc., Menlo Park, California Product Management Lead

- Turned advances in Artificial Intelligence research into product concepts and prototypes for future services (e.g. AI-poweredAR Glasses)
- Led the effort to bring the next billion users on the platform by launching rapid experiments and product features in international markets with high user growth potential
- Built and managed a product team of 7 PMs and orchestrating a team of 50+ engineers, user researchers, designers, data scientists, growth marketers, data engineers, content strategists, and marketers

3/2014 – 9/2018 **Wisdom Collective, Inc.**, San Francisco, California **CEO and Co-Founder**

- Founded Savvy (www.savvy.is) global platform that makes anyone with expertise bookable and connects them with learners for 1:1 learning sessions over live browser-based video chat
- The company is set to revolutionize education by applying the Sharing Economy model to the \$435B online learning market
- Raised \$1.7M Seed from VCs and angels, built a team of 9, developed and launched a product for thousands of teachers and learners
- Successful exit through acquisition

1/2013 – 2/2016 **Singularity Un**

Singularity University, Moffett Field, California **Executive Product Advisor**

- Led SU's effort to bring their Executive Program online
- Developed SU's strategy for interactive web and mobile content to connect their program participants with their exponential innovation topics and to foster community building, international exchange and knowledge transfer

1/2013 - 3/2014

Airbnb, Inc., San Francisco, California

Head of International Product

- Led Airbnb's global product and market strategy to grow the two-sided marketplace and provide supply/demand liquidity across 192 countries
- Directed international growth effort by orchestrating all country leads and teams to define and execute Airbnb's global business strategy
- Provided leadership and strategic advice to the CEO and executive team on company strategy and global product innovation; actively supported key staff as management coach and mentor
- Delivered keynote speeches on Product Excellence and represented Airbnb at numerous international conferences and events

9/2011 - 1/2013

Twitter, Inc., San Francisco, California Senior Product Lead, Head of Global Growth

- Drove Twitter's global strategy and product feature experiments for growing active users to over 250 million
- Led international user research focused on A/B product experiments to identify drivers for rapid user growth in all international markets
- Doubled the number of Twitter users in key markets (like Germany)
- Led the company's international strategy and globalization effort, enabling Twitter to reach every person on the planet
- Orchestrated a community of 800K volunteer translators from the global Twitter community
- Guided the company and leadership team on product development best practices and strategies

11/2010 - 9/2011

Mozilla, Mountain View, California

Principal Product Manager, Mobile

- Launched Firefox on Android millions of downloads, established new standard for mobile HTML5 and "do not track" for mobile browsers
- Represented Mozilla as official spokesperson keynote speaker at CTIA 2011, VentureBeat 2011 Mobile Summit, VentureBeat 2011

3/2006 - 11/2010

Google, Inc., Mountain View, California

Senior Product Manager Google Search Innovation, Business Products

- Led strategic growth projects with Marissa Mayer: drove Google.com background images from inception to global launch resulting in a massive increase of users setting Google as their browser homepage
- Designed and launched iGoogle gadgets and themes in 40+ languages to drive growth to millions of daily active users
- Innovated Google's customer support management system
- Defined strategy and developed technology for launching products in 120+ languages across Google's product portfolio
- Alumnus of Google's EDGE Leadership Program

1/2004 - 2/2006

SAP AG, Walldorf, Germany

Principal Strategist, Corporate Strategy Group, Office of the CEO

- Led strategic projects for SAP's CEO and executive team
- Developed global standards and best-practices for integrating enduser experience into enterprise applications
- Official SAP spokesperson

5/1999 – 12/2003

SAP AG, Walldorf, Germany

Senior Product Lead, SAP Mobile Technology

- Built and managed global, cross-cultural Product Management team of 20 Product Leads and 200 engineers in Europe, US, and Asia
- Led projects to incorporate requirements for global customers from inception to completion, including staffing, project scoping and budgeting
- Increased effectiveness of "SAP Mobile Application Studio" dramatically
- Envisioned and brought to life SAP Application on Microsoft Tablet PC platform - presented by Bill Gates and Jeff Raikes at Microsoft's Tablet PC Launch in Nov 2002 as the first commercial business application for a tablet device

11/1995 - 5/1999

SAP AG, Walldorf, Germany

Developer, Product Manager, SAP Technology Platform

- Architected, designed and developed software tools and applications
- Presented workshops at international events, Partner management
- Directed engineering team in development of software improvements based upon end-user feedback and market requirements

3/1995 - 10/1995

IBM Scientific Research Center Heidelberg, Germany **Research Fellow Student**, AI Lab / Speech Recognition

Engineered AI components for IBM's speech recognition "ViaVoice"

10/1990 – 2/1995 **IBM,** Berlin, Germany

Working Student

- Created commercial software solutions for IBM's system "AS/400"
- Developed interactive multi-media app for Berlin's 2000 Olympic bid

Education

9/1999 – 4/2003 **Berlin Institute of Technology** - Berlin, Germany

PhD in Computer Science with emphasis in Artificial Intelligence Thesis on Expert Systems, Machine Learning, and human-computer interaction of smart software systems and applications

4/1990 – 10/1995 **Berlin Institute of Technology** - Berlin, Germany

M.S. degree in Mathematics and Computer Science, B.S. in Physics

Graduated with top honors

Recipient of Friedrich Ebert Foundation scholarship

Intellectual Property

- US Patent 7302610 Identifying solutions to computer problems in main system by service system in distributed system landscape
- US Patent 7260380 Storing and synchronizing data on a removable storage medium
- US Patent 7257735 Identifying solutions to computer problems in client/server system
- US Patent 7240327 Cross-platform development for devices with heterogeneous capabilities

Publications and Product Portfolio

- Dr. Thomas Arend Contributing Author "<u>Leading Global Innovation</u>" by Karina R. Jensen -June 2017
- Dr. Thomas Arend Contributing Author Elliott Adams "The Startup Mixtape The Guide to Building and Launching A High-Growth Tech Startup" April 2017 http://www.themixtape.co
- <u>Entrepreneur Magazine</u>, March 2016 "One-to-One Teaching Platform Savvy Launches, Tapping a \$105 Billion Market"
- Dr. Thomas Arend Contributing Author "Cracking the PM Interview", 2013
- Dr. Thomas Arend: "Expertenmaschinen Maschinenexperten: Expertensysteme in der kommerziellen Praxis" (<u>Expert Machines – Machine Experts: Commercial Expert Systems</u>)
 Peter Lang Publishing Group, Frankfurt, Berlin, New York, April 2003, ISBN 3-631-51267-8
- Focus Magazine 47 / 2013: German Stars in Silicon Valley Thomas Arend
- Dr. Thomas Arend: Tablet PC Smart Guide, Microsoft Press / Cleverdis, October 2004
- Bill Gates / Jeff Raikes: Speech at Microsoft's International Tablet PC Launch Event, New York City, Nov.7, 2002
- Dr. Thomas Arend: SAP on Tablet PC, online articles and press releases, 2002 2005
- Dr. Thomas Arend: SAP Upgrade Guide / "EnjoySAP" (multi-media CD), SAP Press, 2003
- Dr. Thomas Arend: <u>Product Management Festival 2013</u> Keynote Speech
- Dr. Thomas Arend: <u>Localization Research Forum</u> Keynote Speech
- Portfolio: thomasarend.com

Languages

- German (native), English (fluent), French (conversational), Japanese (basics)
- Triple citizen of U.S., Germany, and France